Many times you must have heard that after 3 years the life insurance company
cannot reject your claim. Many times the advisor
must have sold you such a policy citing section 45 where he must have said that
you better not tell all this information but still you will get this claim. Because under section 45,
companies cannot reject the claim after 3 years. Is this really 100% true?
In this video, I am going to tell you in detail what section 45 actually
is? What is fraud? What is a misstatement? In which cases the insurance
company can challenge and reject your claim even after 3 years?
Watch this video completely because this
is a very important thing for your family's financial planning. Imagine there is a person who is less educated,
has less income but he purchases a term insurance policy by lying and
after 4 years he dies. Will the insurance company give him the full claim keeping in mind section 45
? Watch this video completely. If you find the video helpful, then definitely like, share and
subscribe to my YouTube channel Anil Rajpurohit Triple FS
. There are more than 300 videos
which will help you a lot in financial planning and at the end of the video I will try to tell how
you can make your claim 100% smooth. How to prevent your claim from
getting stuck. What information and what details you have to keep in mind.
Now the policy cannot be challenged after 3 years.
Let us understand important information about section 45 in detail here.
Whenever you purchase a policy, whether it is term insurance, savings plan
or you purchase a policy of any company, you
will definitely find this screen in your policy bond. Where it will be written that the complete details of section 45
will be mentioned in English. In this entire video, I am
going to explain in detail what are the terms and conditions in
this picture that you are seeing . After taking the policy for 3 years, you
cannot challenge it. Why has this section 45 actually been introduced? Earlier, it
used to happen many times that when you used to purchase the policy, there used to be some small
mistake in the proposal form. So on that basis also the insurance companies
used to reject your claim. So now the insurance company
has brought a very good section where you can secure your claim so that
your claim does not get rejected on any small issue. Keeping that in mind, this section
has been created. Now you see that after 3 years the policy is safe. Any life
insurance policy cannot be
cancelled or revoked by the insurance company for any reason after the completion of 3 years
. How will these 3 years be counted? 3 years from the date of issue of the policy. Risk commencement means
3 years after the risk starts. Now you will think what
is the difference between policy issue and risk commencement? For example, let's assume that you purchase an insurance policy from LIC where
there are many policies which you purchase for children.
When the risk for children starts, LIC has some such policies. Like if you
purchase a policy for a 2-year-old child or a 3-year-old child, then there
is a rule that their risk will start after the age of 8 years, so now this 3-year
rule will start for them when they will be 8 years old, after that policy revival, suppose
you purchase a policy and even if you run the policy for 5 years, now in the sixth year you
let the policy lapse and did not pay the premium, then when you revive this policy, then
these 3 years will start again from there. Therefore, always
pay the premium on time. Do not let the policy lapse so that you get the benefit of section 45. Plus
after the date of adding the rider, for example, there is a customer whose name
is Ram. He took the policy on 1 January 2020. After 1 January 23, the insurance company
cannot cancel his policy. It can do so in some cases.
I will also explain that in details later, in which cases the claim can also be rejected
after 3 years. You will understand that too. Now let us
understand the exception in case of cheating or fraud. If we talk about cheating, then if the company
comes to know about the fraud within 3 years, then the company can cancel the policy within a three year.
Like a person purchased the policy. He had diabetes. He did not tell.
After 2 years the company came to know that he had a health condition. The company considered it a fraud.
By considering it as fraud, the company can cancel the policy. It can cancel it
within 3 years. Let us understand the meaning of fraud. Fraud means
knowingly giving false information to the company or hiding the truth or any
such work which the insurance company considers fraud or any such work which is
considered a legal crime or legal fraud. For example, for example, you have a health
condition. You also got a health checkup done. You also have the report but
while taking the policy you will say that I am completely fit. Or you have low income but
you are taking the policy by showing more income so that you get more insurance cover. For example,
you have to purchase term life insurance. Your income is 3 lakhs but you told 5 lakhs so that
you get an insurance cover of ₹ 1 crore. So the company considers this method as fraud
and can cancel your policy within 3 years. I am not talking about the claim
. I am coming to the policy now. Then later we will also talk about the claim. There are many
such situations where if you are silent, that is, the customer who
is buying the policy is silent and has not told anything, then it is not considered fraud. For example,
when you are buying the policy,
there are many questions in the proposal form of the company or the advisor or in your policy. You were not asked questions in that. Like,
do you have stomach ulcer? The customer did not tell because the company
did not ask about it. Okay? So this is not fraud. But if there is a question which
is in your proposal form, the company has asked, but you have not answered it or
have given a false answer, then it will be considered fraud. Like
the information of your existing insurance, you already have hypertension, diabetes or have undergone any kind of operation
, surgery, then there is a question to tell all those things there. There
is a long list. So you have been asked that and if you give a wrong answer to it, then it
will be considered fraud. What will be the exceptions to fraud?
For example, if a mistake is made unknowingly. For example, if the insured or the nominee proves
that they were not aware of that fact. They did not deliberately tell the wrong thing, then
a case of fraud will not be made. The responsibility of giving proof for this will be of
the insured in whose name the insurance is or his nominee. For example,
Sita had given a medical report in which it was written that the blood sugar
is on the borderline. She thought that this is not a disease, so she
did not mention it in the policy form. Later the insurer called her a fraud. But the nominee somehow
proved that she did not intend to do any fraud intentionally. So
the company will not consider it a fraud. Now till now we have talked about fraud. Now
we will talk about misstatement i.e. wrong information. What all
will be there in section 45. If any wrong information or hiding a fact
affects the life expectancy of the insured, then the company can cancel the policy within 3 years. Life
expectancy means suppose you are healthy. You can live till the age of 80. But
you have adopted some such habit due to which your life expectancy of living till 80 years may
be reduced due to that habit. Okay? For example, suppose there is a person who smokes
but he does not mention it in the policy and after 2 years a claim comes, then
the company can say that if we had known that the
person who is taking the insurance policy smokes, then it is possible that we would not have given him the policy at this rate or
would not have issued the policy, so this is a misstatement. Okay?
What will happen in case of a misstatement? The company will return your premium.
What will happen in case of fraud? The company will cancel your policy, it will not return the premium. But
in case of a misstatement, the company will cancel your policy and will also return the premium within
three years. If such a case happens, if the policy is cancelled due to any wrong information or
is cancelled due to a misstatement, then the company
will return your total premium within 90 days. So
after deducting some charges from this you get your money back. Now let's talk
about material fact. A fact will be a material fact only if it
has a direct bearing on the risk. Or it depends on the insurer to prove that if he knew the fact
then he would not have issued the policy. But who will be responsible for proving this fact
? It will be the insurance company. If somebody
has a minor tooth problem, any small problem with the teeth and the customer did not disclose it because it
is not a material fact. But if he has some health problem, heart problem
and he did not disclose it then it is a material fact because it is simply a risk.
Now let us understand this in a summary. After 3 years the policy has been issued. 3
years have been completed. If the company does not cancel your policy then there
is no need for a refund because the policy is not being cancelled. But if you have committed fraud, like
you have hidden your diabetes or have deliberately lied, then
the company can cancel the policy within 3 years. In case of fraud, you will not get a refund. If you
give any wrong information, give a wrong statement. Like you have written your age wrong,
have hidden information about smoking, then the company will not consider it a fraud. But within 3 years the policy
will be cancelled and your paid premium will be refunded after deducting some charges
. And in some cases if you are silent, remain quiet because you
were not asked any question, so you did not answer, then it will not be considered a fraud, so
the policy will continue.
Now let us understand a little in simple language. What will happen in fraud? The policy will be cancelled,
there will be no refund. In case of a misstatement, the policy will be cancelled. You will get a refund. The policy is safe after 3 years
. The company cannot cancel it. And in the case of age, suppose there
was a slight mismatch in your age. So your premium or
policy will be adjusted according to that age but the policy will not be cancelled.
Now let us see case one, like someone tells wrong income or wrong education
. Suppose someone deliberately told that he was 10th pass but he was a graduate. His income
was less but he told more. The company
will have the right to challenge and cancel the policy within 3 years. Exception: If 3 years have passed, then the company cannot cancel the policy on this basis
. But section 45 says that if the policy holder proves
that he did not lie intentionally, then only he will be protected. But if the insurance
company proves that he has lied, then the policy
can be cancelled even after 3 years. Even the claim cannot be received. We will understand the case further.
It is necessary to prove fraud after 3 years in case of claim. If it
has been 3 years since you took the policy, then the company
can reject your claim only by proving fraud. If it has been 3 years since you took the policy, then now
it will be the responsibility of the company to prove fraud that you have committed fraud, only then they can reject the claim
. If they cannot prove fraud, then they
cannot reject your claim even after 3 years . That is, if a company
gets documented proof that the policy director has taken the plan by lying. Like less
income is shown in ITR but they had shown more in the form.
So the company can still stop the claim by making a case in front of the court or RRDA. That is,
many times there are term insurance policies, where
term policies are available at a slightly cheaper rate on high income. So sometimes the customer's income is ₹ 45 lakh
and the term plan is available even on an income of 5 lakh. So the customer says that he
can buy the policy for an income of Rs. 5 lakh. But if an early claim comes in the future,
the company checks his income documents and the income appears to be less than the actual income
and if this is less, then the insurance company can also go to IRDA and tell that
he had lied. His actual income was less. If he had taken the policy by telling more,
then it is possible that your claim may get rejected. That is, section 45 does not protect against fraud
. It is only a genuine mistake. It only protects against misunderstanding.
Listen carefully again. Section 45 protects
only genuine mistakes or misunderstandings, not fraud
. Let us understand in simple terms that the mistake is genuine. If your mistake is genuine, like
some typing error occurred while writing, which can also be done by the advisor, or if the knowledge was limited, then you
will get a claim in that, but if you have deliberately lied, like you,
for taking a term policy, for example, I am repeatedly talking about term policy,
like to take a term policy, you need to be an education graduate.
But you were only 12th pass. But in the form you mentioned that I am a graduate.
In that case also, you lied about your policy. If the company proves this fraud, then it
can reject the claim. Let us understand through a case study. Suppose this is a real
case study. Where there is an insurance holder named Anoop Thadani. He had purchased the policy
of STFT Life . There was a claim of 13 lakhs. After the death of the father,
the insurance company rejected the claim for some reason. The company HTFC
Life said that Anup
had a pre-existing disease with his ex-wife, such as heart disease or blood pressure.
They were not told about this and if they had given the correct information in the policy, we
would not have given them this policy. But
what decision did the consumer firm take then that it could not prove fraud. In this case,
the insurance company only told that they had all these health issues. But the
insurance company could not prove that they really had a health
problem. Only the misstatement was considered by them. That is, it was considered wrong information.
So even after 3 years of wrong information, if it has been 3 years and you
get a claim, then that claim had to be given to the company because the insurance company
could not prove that they had committed fraud. That is why the consumer Vadodara District Consumer
Firm accepted that section 454 is applicable. If the policy holder
was under the policy for more than 3 years, then the misstatement can be considered only on the basis that
has less direct impact on the risk. Now here he was also given the full ₹ 1 lakh. Along with 9% interest,
he was given this full claim. Now let's understand the important points of section 45.
3 year rule The period of 3 years does not mean that you
will get the claim after giving wrong information. Effect of fraud. If the fraud
is done intentionally then the company has full right to stop the claim. But they
have to prove the fraud. If any information has been hidden which can have serious consequences, it
will be necessary for the company to prove the material fact and if they prove it
then they can reject the claim.
But if the company is unable to prove it then the claim will be received. What
is the best strategy to take an insurance policy? Tell the truth.
Now let's understand with an example. This is also a real example of LIC vs Sushila Devi ji
where she had purchased the policy from LIC. In the proposal form, she wrote that
she did not have any disease. Whereas in reality Sushila ji had kidney and heart disease
and was already undergoing treatment. Now after 4 years of taking the policy, she
died. The nominee made a claim. But LIC somehow
proved from the hospital records that the customer already had health issues. So the company
considered it a fraud and the result was that the claim was rejected.
Let's understand another real life example. Where there was LIC vs Money Manish Gupta ji. It
was the decision of Rajasthan High Court. Where Gupta ji wrote that I
am completely healthy. I do not have any diabetes or liver or any problem. Whereas in fact he
had diabetes and he also had liver related problems. He died 5 years after taking the policy
. The company proved in the court that
he had hidden these things. So his claim was also rejected.
Let's take another example. LIC vs Aasar Rani is the decision of Punjab and Haryana High Court. Where
he had written in the form that he is a non-smoker and non-drinker. Neither does he
smoke, which means he does not consume tobacco and neither does he take alcohol
. Whereas when he died, it was found in the hospital records that
he was a chronic alcoholic and smoker. The company somehow managed it through the hospital records
and proved that it was a fraud, so their claim was also rejected
. So many people think that if they hide it now, the company
will not find out. Insurance companies find out.
Now what is the final sick thing for you? What is the lesson to learn?
See, after 3 years, normally if there is a miss statement or a normal mistake,
you will get the claim in that case, but if you have made a claim intentionally, then
even after 10 years, your claim can be rejected. Now let us understand from three examples.
Case One LIC One Sushila Devi ji had kidney and heart problems, she hid it,
even after 4 years she died, the claim was rejected. LIC vs Manish Gupta ji
had diabetes and liver problems, she hid it, death did not happen after 5 years, still
the claim was rejected. LIC vs Asha Rana ji, she was a smoker and an alcoholic,
she hid both the things. Even if the death happened after 6 years, the case was rejected. These
are real love stories.
Finally, if I summarize this video, then I think it must have become quite clear to you now
that in which case you will get the claim. In which case your claim can be rejected even
after 3 years . What things do you have to keep in mind? First of all
, when you purchase a policy, you think that you
have given the information honestly and truthfully. But has the advisor
written the same truthfully in your proposal form? So when the policy bond comes to your home, do open the policy bond. There
You will get the proposal form. Check the details there again. Are there any spelling errors?
Has your education been written incorrectly? Has your policy been given
by exaggerating your income? Has your existing insurance information been hidden
? Suppose you had mentioned a health condition but your advisor did not
write it or forgot to write it. Humans can also make mistakes. So
when the proposal form comes to your home, do check it once again to see if all
the information is correct or not. Because tomorrow if you have not checked the proposal form
and tomorrow some such incident happens, you may face problems in the claim. Secondly, this
is not related to section 45. But still I am telling you an important thing that whenever
you purchase any insurance policy, at least tell your family members that
I have purchased the policy. Because around ₹2-22,000 crores are lying with LIC.
Other companies also have thousands of crores lying with them. Where no one
came to claim. Because the family members do not know that you had taken a policy and
if you died, they did not go to the company to claim. They do not even have any documents
because the documents were left in your office or were kept somewhere else or
are in electronic mode only, so whenever you purchase a policy,
do tell your family members and children that I have taken an insurance policy. Do check the proposal form and if
you feel that there is a mismatch between the information you gave and the information in the proposal form
or it is written wrongly, then you can get it rectified by emailing the company
. Or you also want to take a free look at the policy by emailing the company.
Without email, you can go to the company's website or go to the company's office and take a free look
and also get the money back. So you must keep all this information in mind
so that your claim does not stop. Because many times you are telling the truth. The agent
can also make a mistake. Many times you may get influenced by an agent or someone
while purchasing a small policy . So don't do this because
if you purchase a big policy like term insurance for your family, especially or any other, the
best way to claim is to tell the truth in the proposal form, your claim
will never be rejected. The claim settlement
ratio of most of the top insurance companies is 99 something percent. They are giving more than 99% claims. One or two or half%
are not getting any claim anywhere. So all the customers
are not Raja Harishchandra. Now, even the customers hide a lot of things in today's date
. I have also been working in the industry for 15 years. I know how to
buy a policy or to get a bigger insurance cover or to
not increase the premium a little. They hide smoking things. They hide their health conditions.
Instead of physical medical, they agree on video medical so that
their report is not caught in the physical medical. So many such things happen. So honestly
give all the information in the policy. Your claim will never be rejected. If still
there is any problem, then you can go to IRDA. You can go to Obligation. You
can go to Insurance Protection. You can go to Consumer Form. And if you
have given all the correct information, then your claim will never be rejected.
If you found the video helpful, then before leaving please like,
share and subscribe to my YouTube channel Anil Rajpurohit Triple FS. Thank you so much. Jai Hind.